I'm going to try and explain why it is that perhaps
سأحول أن أشرح لماذا من المحتمل
we don't understand as much as we think we do.
أننا لا نفهم بقدر ما نظن أننا نفعل.
I'd like to begin with four questions.
أود أن أبدأ بأربعة أسئلة.
This is not some sort of cultural thing for the time of year.
هذا ليس شيئا ثقافياً لهذا الوقت من العام.
That's an in-joke, by the way.
هذة نكتة ضمنية ، بالمناسبة.
But these four questions, actually,
ولكن هذه الأسئلة الأربعة، فى الحقيقة،
are ones that people who even know quite a lot about science find quite hard.
هي تلك الأسئلة التي حتى الأشخاص الذين يعرفون الكثير عن العلم يجدونها صعبة جداً.
And they're questions that I've asked of science television producers,
وهي أسئلة قد طرحتها على منتجي برامج تلفزيونية علمية،
of audiences of science educators --
لمستمعين من مدرسي العلوم--
so that's science teachers -- and also of seven-year-olds,
وإذاً فهؤلاء معلمي العلوم -- وأيضاً الذين تتراوح أعمارهم بين سبع سنوات،
and I find that the seven-year-olds do marginally better
ووجدت أن الذين أعمارهم سبع سنوات يؤدون أفضل بنسبة بسيطة
than the other audiences, which is somewhat surprising.
من المستعمين الأخرين ، و التى أجد أنه شى يثير الدهشة إلى حد ما.
So the first question, and you might want to write this down,
السؤال الأول هو، ربما تودوا أن تكتبوا السؤال
either on a bit of paper, physically, or a virtual piece of paper
على قطعة من الورق، فعلياً، أو قطعة من الورق إفتراضياً
in your head. And, for viewers at home, you can try this as well.
في أذهانكم، وبالنسبة للمشاهدين في المنازل، ربما تودوا أن تفعلوا هذا أيضاً.
A little seed weighs next to nothing and a tree weighs a lot, right?
البذور لا تزن شئ تقريباً ، و الشجرة تزن الكثير، أليس كذلك؟
I think we agree on that. Where does the tree get the stuff that makes up this chair,
أعتقد أننا نتفق حول ذلك. من أين تأتي الأشجار بالأشياء التي تشكل هذا الكرسي،
right? Where does all this stuff come from?
اليس كذلك؟ من أين تأتي كل تلك الأشياء؟
(Knocks)
(طرق)
And your next question is, can you light a little torch-bulb
و السؤال الثاني هو، هل يمكنك إضاءة مصباح شعلة صغير
with a battery, a bulb and one piece of wire?
بواسطة بطارية، مصباح و قطعة من الأسلاك؟
And would you be able to, kind of, draw a -- you don't have to draw
وهل ستتمكن، نوعاً ما، من رسم -- لا يتوجب عليكم رسم
the diagram, but would you be able to draw the diagram,
المخطط، و لكن هل ستكون قادر على رسم المخطط
if you had to do it? Or would you just say,
إذا كان يتوجب عليكم فعل ذلك، أم ستقولوا فقط
that's actually not possible?
انه فى الحقيقة مستحيل؟
The third question is, why is it hotter in summer than in winter?
السؤال الثالث هو لماذا الصيف أكثر سخونة من الشتاء؟
I think we can probably agree that it is hotter in summer than in winter,
أعتقد أنه من المرجح أننا نتفق أن الصيف أكثر سخونة من الشتاء،
but why? And finally, would you be able to --
ولكن لماذا؟ و أخيراً، هل ستكون قادر على --
and you can sort of scribble it, if you like --
يمكنكم، نوعاً ما، أن تخربشوا إذا أردتم--
scribble a plan diagram of the solar system,
خربشات مخطط للنظام الشمسي ،
showing the shape of the planets' orbits?
مظهرين أشكال مدارات الكواكب؟
Would you be able to do that?
هل ستكونوا قادرين على ان تفعلوا ذلك؟
And if you can, just scribble a pattern.
وإذا كنت تستطيع ، خربشات مجرد نمط.
OK. Now, children get their ideas not from teachers,
حسناً. الأطفال يحصلون على أفكارهم -- ليس من مدرسيهم،
as teachers often think, but actually from common sense,
كما يعتقد المدرسين غالباً، ولكن من الحس السليم،
from experience of the world around them,
من تجارب العالم من حولهم،
from all the things that go on between them and their peers,
من جميع الأشياء التي تحدث ما بينهم و بين أقرانهم،
and their carers, and their parents, and all of that. Experience.
ومن يقومون برعايتهم، وأبائهم، وذلك كله، الخبرة.
And one of the great experts in this field, of course, was, bless him,
وأحد الخبراء العظماء فى هذا المجال، بطبيعة الحال، كان، باركة الله،
Cardinal Wolsey. Be very careful what you get into people's heads
الكاردينال ولسي. كن حذراً جداً حيال ما تضعه فى عقول الناس
because it's virtually impossible to shift it afterwards, right?
لأنه من المستحيل أن تحول تفكيرهم عنه بعد ذلك، أليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm not quite sure how he died, actually.
فى الواقع أنا لست متأكد تماماً كيف مات.
Was he beheaded in the end, or hung?
هل كان مقطوع الرأس فى النهاية، أو مشنوق؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, those questions, which, of course, you've got right,
والأن، تلك الأسئلة، التى بالطبع قد كتبتوها،
and you haven't been conferring, and so on.
والتي لم تتداولوها بعد ، و هلم جرا،
And I -- you know, normally, I would pick people out and humiliate,
وأنا -- كما تعلمون ، في العادة ، أقوم باختيار الناس ، وإذلالهم ،
but maybe not in this instance.
ولكن ربما ليس في هذا الموقف.
A little seed weighs a lot and, basically, all this stuff,
البذرة الصغيرة تزن الكثير، وفى الحقيقة، كل هذه الأشياء،
99 percent of this stuff, came out of the air.
99 بالمئة من هذه المادة، جاءت من الهواء.
Now, I guarantee that about 85 percent of you, or maybe it's fewer at TED,
والأن، أنا أؤكد أن 85 بالمئة منكم، أو ربما أقل هنا فى تيد،
will have said it comes out of the ground. And some people,
سيقولوا أنها تأتي من الأرض، وبعض الناس،
probably two of you, will come up and argue with me afterwards,
ربما إثنان منكم، سيأتوا و يتجادلوا معي بعد حين،
and say that actually, it comes out of the ground.
ويقولون في الحقيقة أن المادة تأتي من الأرض.
Now, if that was true, we'd have trucks going round the country,
والأن، إذا كان ذلك صحيح، سيكون لدينا شاحنات تجوب أرجاء الدولة،
filling people's gardens in with soil, it'd be a fantastic business.
تملأ حدائق الأشخاص بالتربة، سيكون عمل رائع.
But, actually, we don't do that.
ولكن، نحن لا نفعل ذلك فى الحقيقة.
The mass of this comes out of the air.
إن كتلة هذا تأتي من الهواء.
Now, I passed all my biology exams in Britain.
الأن، لقد نجحت فى جميع إمتحانات الأحياء، فى بريطانيا
I passed them really well, but I still came out of school
لقد نجحت فيهم جيداً حقاً، ولكنى خرجت من المدرسة
thinking that that stuff came out of the ground.
ولا زلت أعتقد أن هذه المادة تأتي من الأرض.
Second one: can you light a little torch-bulb with a battery bulb and one piece of wire?
السؤال الثاني، هل يمكن إضاءة مصباح صغير بواسطة بطارية و مصباح و قطعة من الأسلاك؟
Yes, you can, and I'll show you in a second how to do that.
نعم، يمكن ذلك، و سوف أريكم خلال ثواني كيف يمكن عمل ذلك.
Now, I have some rather bad news,
الأن، لدي بعض الأنباء الغير سارة،
which is that I had a piece of video that I was about to show you,
وهي أنه كان لدة مقتطف من فيديو كنت ساعرضه عليكم،
which unfortunately -- the sound doesn't work in this room,
ولكن لسوء الحظ -- الصوت لا يعمل فى هذه الغرفة،
so I'm going to describe to you, in true "Monty Python" fashion,
ولذلك سأصف لكم، بطريقة مونتى باثون،
what happens in the video. And in the video, a group of researchers
ما يحدث فى الفيديو. و فى هذا الفيديو، مجموعة من الباحثين
go to MIT on graduation day.
ذهبوا إلى معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا (أم أي تي) في يوم التخرج.
We chose MIT because, obviously, that's a very long way away
لقد اخترنا معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا ، لأنه من الواضح ، أنه بعيد جداً
from here, and you wouldn't mind too much,
من هنا، و أنكم لن تمانعوا كثيرا،
but it sort of works the same way in Britain
ولكنه يعمل بنفس الطريقة نوعاً ما فى بريطانيا
and in the West Coast of the USA.
و الساحل الغربي من الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية،
And we asked them these questions, and we asked those questions
وسألناهم هذه الأسئلة، و سألنا هذه الأسئلة
of science graduates, and they couldn't answer them.
إلى خريجي قسم العلوم ، و لم يستطيعوا الإجابة عنها.
And so, there's a whole lot of people saying,
ولذلك، هنالك العديد من الناس يقولون،
"I'd be very surprised if you told me that this came out of the air.
"سأكون مندهشاً للغاية اذا قلت لي ان هذا جاء من الهواء.
That's very surprising to me." And those are science graduates.
ذلك مُدهش جداً بالنسبة لي." و هؤلاء هم خريجي علوم.
And we intercut it with, "We are the premier science university in the world,"
ونحن ننهي بـ : "أننا جامعة العلوم الرائدة في العالم،"
because of British-like hubris.
لأن البريطانيون يحبون الغطرسة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when we gave graduate engineers that question,
وعندما أعطينا خريجي هندسة ذلك السؤال،
they said it couldn't be done.
قالو أن هذا لا يمكن أن يحدث.
And when we gave them a battery, and a piece of wire, and a bulb,
وعندما أعطيناهم بطارية و قطعة من الأسلاك، و مصباح
and said, "Can you do it?" They couldn't do it. Right?
وقلنا، "هل يمكنكم فعل ذلك؟" لم يتمكنوا. أليس كذلك؟
And that's no different from Imperial College in London, by the way,
وبالمناسبة، هذا لا يختلف عن الكلية الملكية، فى لندن،
it's not some sort of anti-American thing going on.
الأمر ليس شىء ما مناهض للولايات المتحدة الأمريكية.
As if. Now, the reason this matters is we pay lots and lots of money
كما لو. الآن ، السبب في هذه المسائل هو أننا ندفع الكثير والكثير من المال
for teaching people -- we might as well get it right.
لتعليم الناس، وقد نتمكن من الحصول عليها بطريقة صحيحة.
And there are also some societal reasons
وهناك أيضا بعض الأسباب الإجتماعية
why we might want people to understand what it is that's happening
لماذا ربما نريد أن يفهم الناس ما الذي يحدث
in photosynthesis. For example, one half of the carbon equation
في التمثيل الضوئي. على سبيل المثال ، نصف معادلة الكربون
is how much we emit, and the other half of the carbon equation,
هو كم ما نقوم بنفثه، و النصف الأخر من معادلة الكربون،
as I'm very conscious as a trustee of Kew,
وأنا واعي جداً ، كوصي من حدائق "كيو" ،
is how much things soak up, and they soak up carbon dioxide out of the atmosphere.
كم هي الأشياء التى تمتص، وأنها تمتص ثاني أكسيد الكربون
That's what plants actually do for a living.
وهذا هو ما تفعله النباتات للعيش.
And, for any Finnish people in the audience, this is a Finnish pun:
وبالنسبة لأي أشخاص من فنلندا في الحضور ،هذه هي لعبة الكلمات الفنلندية ،
we are, both literally and metaphorically, skating on thin ice
نحن ، على حد سواء حرفيا ومجازيا ، نتزحلق على جليد رقيق
if we don't understand that kind of thing.
إذا لم نفهم مثل هذه الأشياء.
Now, here's how you do the battery and the bulb.
الأن، هاهي كيفية عمل البطارية و المصباح
It's so easy, isn't it? Of course, you all knew that.
إنها سهلة جداً، أليس كذلك؟ بالطبع، جميعكم كان يعلم ذلك.
But if you haven't played with a battery and a bulb,
إذا لم تلعبوا ببطارية و مصباح،
if you've only seen a circuit diagram,
إذا كنتم قد رأيتم فقط مخطط الدائرة،
you might not be able to do that, and that's one of the problems.
قد لا تكونوا قادرين على فعل ذلك، و هذه هي أحدى المشاكل.
So, why is it hotter in summer than in winter?
إذا، لماذا الصيف أكثر سخونة من الشتاء؟
We learn, as children, that you get closer to something that's hot,
تعلمنا، عندما كنا أطفال، أنه إذا أقتربنا من شئ ساخن جداً،
and it burns you. It's a very powerful bit of learning,
فإنة سيحرقك. إنها جزئية جبارة جداً في التعلم ،
and it happens pretty early on.
ويحدث ذلك في وقت مبكر جداً.
By extension, we think to ourselves, "Why it's hotter in summer than in winter
وبالتالي ، نرى لأنفسنا ، لماذا الجو اكثر حرارة في الصيف من في الشتاء
must be because we're closer to the Sun."
لأننا أقرب إلى الشمس.
I promise you that most of you will have got that.
أعدكم أن معظمكم يظن ذلك.
Oh, you're all shaking your heads,
أوه، الجميع يهز رأسه
but only a few of you are shaking your heads very firmly.
ولكن القليل منكم يهز رأسه بحزم،
Other ones are kind of going like this. All right.
وأخرين، يهزوا هكذا. حسناً.
It's hotter in summer than in winter because the rays from the Sun
إن الصيف أكثر سخونة من الشتاء لأن الأشعة من الشمس،
are spread out more, right, because of the tilt of the Earth.
تنتشر بشكل أوسع، أليس كذلك، بسبب ميلان الأرض.
And if you think the tilt is tilting us closer, no, it isn't.
وإذا كنتم تعتقدوا أن الميلان يقربنا أكثر، فذلك غير صحيح.
The Sun is 93 million miles away, and we're tilting like this, right?
الشمس على بعد 93 مليون ميل، ونحن نميل هكذا، أليس كذلك؟
It makes no odds. In fact, in the Northern Hemisphere,
ليس هناك خلاف ، في الواقع ، في نصف الكرة الشمالي
we're further from the Sun in summer,
نحن أبعد من الشمس في الصيف،
as it happens, but it makes no odds, the difference.
وكما يحدث ، لكنها لا تحدث أي خلاف أو فرق.
OK, now, the scribble of the diagram of the solar system.
حسنا ، الآن ، من خربشات الرسم التخطيطي للنظام الشمسي.
If you believe, as most of you probably do,
إذا كنتم تعتقدون، كما يعتقد معظمكم،
that it's hotter in summer than in winter because we're closer to the Sun,
ان الصيف أكثر سخونة من الشتاء بسبب أننا قريبين من الشمس،
you must have drawn an ellipse.
لابد أن تكونوا قد رسمتم دائرة.
Right? That would explain it, right?
أليس كذلك؟ ذلك يفسر الأمر؟
Except, in your -- you're nodding -- now, in your ellipse,
بإستثناء، فى ال -- أنتم تومئون-- الأن، فى فلككم،
have you thought, "Well, what happens during the night?"
هل فكرتم، " حسناً، ما الذى يحدث خلال الليل ؟"
Between Australia and here, right, they've got summer
بين أستراليا و هنا، أليس كذلك، لديهم صيف
and we've got winter, and what --
و لدينا نحن شتاء، و إذا--
does the Earth kind of rush towards the Sun at night,
هل كانت الأرض تسرع نحو الشمس فى الليل،
and then rush back again? I mean, it's a very strange thing going on,
ثم تعود مرة أخرى؟ أعني، أن شئ غريب جداً يحدث،
and we hold these two models in our head, of what's right and what isn't right,
ونحن نحمل هذين النموذجين في رؤوسنا ، من ما هو صحيح وما هو غير الصحيح ،
and we do that, as human beings, in all sorts of fields.
ونحن نفعل ذلك، كبشر، في شتى المجالات.
So, here's Copernicus' view of what the solar system looked like as a plan.
لذلك ، وهنا رأي كوبرنيكوس في أن النظام الشمسي يشبه المخطط ،
That's pretty much what you should have on your piece of paper. Right?
هذا أشبه بما ينبغي أن يكون قد رُسم على قطعة الورق الخاصة بكم إلى حد كبير. أليس كذلك؟
And this is NASA's view. They're stunningly similar.
وهذا هو رأي ناسا. إنها مماثلة إلى حد مذهل.
I hope you notice the coincidence here.
أتمنى أن تكونوا قد لاحظتم المصادفة هنا.
What would you do if you knew that people had this misconception,
ما الذي ستفعلوه إذا علمتم أن الناس كان لها هذا الإعتقاد الخاطئ،
right, in their heads, of elliptical orbits
أليس كذلك، فى رؤوسهم، حول المدارات البيضاوية
caused by our experiences as children?
بسبب تجاربنا كأطفال؟
What sort of diagram would you show them of the solar system,
ما شكل مخطط النظام الشمسي الذي ستعرضونه عليهم،
to show that it's not really like that?
لتبينوا أنه لا يشبة ذلك حقاً ؟
You'd show them something like this, wouldn't you?
ستعرضون عليهم شئ يشبه هذا، أليس كذلك؟
It's a plan, looking down from above.
إنها مخطط، بالنظر إلى أسفل من أعلى.
But, no, look what I found in the textbooks.
ولكن، لا، أنظروا ماذا وجدت فى الكتب المدرسية،
That's what you show people, right? These are from textbooks,
هذا ما تعرضونه على الناس، أليس كذلك؟ هذا من الكتب المدرسية،
from websites, educational websites --
من مواقع الإنترنت، المواقع التعليمية،
and almost anything you pick up is like that.
من أي شئ تلتقطوه من هذا القبيل تقريباً
And the reason it's like that is because it's dead boring
والسبب أنه هكذا هو أنه لمن الممل جداً
to have a load of concentric circles,
وجود كثير من الدوائر متحدة المركز،
whereas that's much more exciting, to look at something at that angle,
في حين أن هذا هو أكثر إثارة ، أن ننظر إلى شيء من هذه الزاوية ،
isn't it? Right? And by doing it at that angle,
أليس كذلك؟ وفعل ذلك من هذه الزاوية ،
if you've got that misconception in your head, then that
إذا كنت قد حصلت على هذا الإعتقاد الخاطئ في رأسك ، بأن
two-dimensional representation of a three-dimensional thing will be ellipses.
التمثيل ثنائي الأبعاد لشيء ثلاثي الأبعاد سيكون أشكال بيضاوية.
So you've -- it's crap, isn't it really? As we say.
إذاً فأنت كنت -- انها هراء ، أليس كذلك حقا ، كما نقول نحن؟
So, these mental models -- we look for evidence that reinforces our models.
لذلك ، مع هذه النماذج العقلية ، نحن نبحث عن أدلة تعضد ما لدينا من نماذج.
We do this, of course, with matters of race, and politics, and everything else,
ونحن نفعل ذلك ، بطبيعة الحال ، مع مسائل العرق ، والسياسة ، وكل شيء آخر ،
and we do it in science as well. So we look, just look --
ونحن نفعل ذلك في مجال العلوم كذلك. لذلك نحن ننظر -- مجرد النظر --
and scientists do it, constantly -- we look for evidence
والعلماء يفعلون ذلك ، على الدوام -- أن نبحث عن أدلة
that reinforces our models, and some folks are just all too able
تعزز ما لدينا من نماذج ، وبعض الناس ليست سوى قادرة أيضاً
and willing to provide the evidence that reinforces the models.
وعلى استعداد لتقديم الأدلة التي تعزز النماذج.
So, being I'm in the United States, I'll have a dig at the Europeans.
لذا ، كونى في الولايات المتحدة ، وسوف أدقق على الأوروبيين.
These are examples of what I would say is bad practice in science
هذه أمثلة على ما ، أود أن أقوله هو ممارسة سيئة في مجال العلم ،
teaching centers. These pictures are from La Villette in France
نوع من مراكز التعليم. هذه الصور من لا فيليت في فرنسا ،
and the welcome wing of the Science Museum in London.
وجناح الترحيب فى متحف العلوم بلندن.
And, if you look at the, kind of the way these things are constructed,
وإذا نظرتم إلى ، الطريقة التي يتم بها بناء هذه الأشياء ،
there's a lot of mediation by glass, and it's very blue, and kind of professional --
هناك الكثير من وساطة من الزجاج ، وانها زرقاء جدا ، ونوعا ما إحترافية ،
in that way that, you know, Woody Allen comes up
وبهذه الطريقة جاء وودي ألن
from under the sheets in that scene in "Annie Hall,"
من تحت الرقائق ، في ذلك المشهد في قاعة آني ،
and said, "God, that's so professional." And that you don't --
وقال : "يا إلهي ، ذلك عمل محترف جداً " ، وأنك لا --
there's no passion in it, and it's not hands on, right,
لا يوجد فيه شغف ، وانه ليس عملي ، حسنا،
and, you know, pun intended. Whereas good interpretation --
و، كما تعلمون ، يقصد التورية. لكن التفسير جيد،
I'll use an example from nearby -- is San Francisco Exploratorium,
سوف أستخدم مثال من قريب ،إستكشاف سان فرانسيسكو ،
where all the things that -- the demonstrations, and so on,
حيث كل الأشياء التي -- المظاهرات ، وهلم جرا ،
are made out of everyday objects that children can understand,
هي مصنوعة من أشياء من الحياة اليومية يمكن أن يفهمها الأطفال ،
it's very hands-on, and they can engage with, and experiment with.
انها جدا عملية جداً، ويمكنهم التعامل معها ، وتجربتها.
And I know that if the graduates at MIT
وأنا أعلم أنه إذا كان لدى خريجي معهد ماساتشوستس للتكنولوجيا
and in the Imperial College in London had had the battery and the wire
و الكلية الملكية في لندن البطارية والأسلاك ،
and the bit of stuff, and you know, been able to do it,
والقليل من الاشياء ، وكما تعلمون ، سيكونوا قادرين على القيام بذلك ،
they would have learned how it actually works,
وسيكونوا قد تعلموا كيف تعمل فى الواقع،
rather than thinking that they follow circuit diagrams and can't do it.
بدلاً من التفكير فى أن يتبعوا مخطط الدائرة وهم غير قادرين على القيام بذلك.
So good interpretation is more about
لذلك فالتفسير الجيد يدور حول
things that are bodged and stuffed and of my world, right?
الأشياء المدبجة والمحشوة، وعن عالمي، أليس كذلك ؟
And things that -- where there isn't an extra barrier
والأشياء التي -- حيث لا يوجد حاجز اضافي
of a piece of glass or machined titanium,
لقطعة من الزجاج ، أو تشكيلة التيتانيوم،
and it all looks fantastic, OK?
ويبدو كل شيء رائع ، أليس كذلك؟
And the Exploratorium does that really, really well.
والاستكشاف يفعل ذلك حقا ، بشكل جيد ،
And it's amateur, but amateur in the best sense,
وانه من الهواة ، ولكن للهواة في أحسن الحالات،
in other words, the root of the word being of love and passion.
وبعبارة أخرى ، جذر الكلمة يجري من الحب والعاطفة.
So, children are not empty vessels, OK?
ولذلك، الأطفال ليسوا أوعية فارغة، أليس كذلك؟
So, as "Monty Python" would have it,
لذا ، كما كان عليه مونتي بيثون ،
this is a bit Lord Privy Seal to say so,
هذا هو ختم اللورد برايفي لقول ذلك،
but this is -- children are not empty vessels.
ولكن هذا يعني أن الأطفال ليسوا أوعية فارغة.
They come with their own ideas and their own theories,
وهم يأتوا مع أفكارهم ونظرياتهم الخاصة ،
and unless you work with those, then you won't be able to shift them,
وإلا إذا كنت تعمل مع تلك ، فإنك سوف لن تكون قادرعلى تحويلهم ،
right? And I probably haven't shifted your ideas
أليس كذلك؟ من المرجح أننى لم أتمكن من تحويل أفكاركم أيضاً
of how the world and universe operates, either.
حول كيف يعمل العالم و الكون.
But this applies, equally, to matters of trying to sell new technology.
ولكن هذا ينطبق ، على قدم المساواة ، على المسائل المتعلقة بكيفية بيع التكنولوجيا الجديدة.
For example, we are, in Britain, we're trying to do a digital switchover
على سبيل المثال ، نحن -- في بريطانيا ، نحاول القيام بتحول رقمي
of the whole population into digital technology [for television].
من مجموع السكان في التكنولوجيا الرقمية على شاشة التلفزيون.
And it's one of the difficult things
وأنة من أصعب الأشياء،
is that when people have preconceptions of how it all works,
هو أنة عندما يكون لدى الناس أفكار مُسبقة حول كيفية عمل الأشياء،
it's quite difficult to shift those.
فإنة من الصعب تحويل تلك الأفكار.
So we're not empty vessels; the mental models that we have
لذلك نحن لسنا أوعية فارغة ، النماذج الذهنية التي لدينا
as children persist into adulthood.
كأطفال تصل لسن البلوغ.
Poor teaching actually does more harm than good.
التعليم الضعيف يضر أكثر فى الواقع مما ينفع.
In this country and in Britain, magnetism is understood better
فى هذا البلد، وفى بريطانيا، المغناطيسية تفهم بشكل أكثر
by children before they've been to school than afterwards, OK?
لدى الأطفال قبل ذهابهم للمدارس وما بعد ذلك
Same for gravity, two concepts, so it's -- which is quite humbling,
نفس الشئ بالنسبة للجاذبية ، مفهومين ، لذلك -- هذا تحقير للغاية ،
as a, you know, if you're a teacher, and you look before and after,
إذا كنت مدرسا ، وأنت تنظر من قبل وبعد ،
that's quite worrying. They do worse in tests afterwards, after the teaching.
هذا مقلق للغاية. أداؤهم أسوأ في الاختبارات بعد ذلك ، بعد التدريس.
And we collude. We design tests,
نحن نتأمر، ونصمم الإمتحانات،
or at least in Britain, so that people pass them. Right?
وعلى الأقل فى بريطانيا، بحيث ينجح فيها الناس . أليس كذلك؟
And governments do very well. They pat themselves on the back.
الحكومات تعمل بشكل جيد. إنهم يربتوا على ظهورهم.
OK? We collude, and actually if you --
حسناً؟ نحن نتأمر، فى الحقيقة إذا--
if someone had designed a test for me
صمم لي شخص ما إختبار
when I was doing my biology exams,
عندما كنت أمتحن إمتحان البيولوجيا،
to really understand, to see whether I'd understood
ليرى إذا كنت قد فهمت حقاً -- ليرى ما إذا كنت قد فهمت
more than just kind of putting starch and iodine together
أكثر من مجرد وضع النشا و اليود معاً،
and seeing it go blue,
ورؤيتهم يتحولوا إلى اللون الأزرق،
and really understood that plants took their mass out of the air,
وفهم أن النباتات تحصل على كتلتها من الهواء،
then I might have done better at science.
ربما أؤدي بشكل أفضل فى العلوم.
So the most important thing is to get people to articulate their models.
لذلك فإن أهم شيء هو تعبيرالناس عن نماذجها.
Your homework is -- you know, how does an aircraft's wing create lift?
الواجب المنزلي الخاص بك -- هل تعلموا ، كيف يقوم جناح طائرة بعملية التحليق؟
An obvious question, and you'll have an answer now in your heads.
السؤال الذي يطرح نفسه ، وسيكون لديك الآن جوابا في رؤوسكم ،
And the second question to that then is,
والسؤال الثاني هو،
ensure you've explained how it is that planes can fly upside down.
تأكد من أنك شرحت كيف يمكن للطائرات الطيران رأساً على عقب.
Ah ha, right. Second question is, why is the sea blue? All right?
اَه، حسناً. السؤال الثاني هو، لماذا البحر أزرق اللون؟ أليس كذلك ؟
And you've all got an idea in your head of the answer.
وجميعكم لديه فكرة فى رأسه عن الجواب.
So, why is it blue on cloudy days? Ah, see.
حسناً، لماذا يكون أزرق اللون فى الأيام الملبدة بالغيوم؟ اَه، أرايتم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I've always wanted to say that in this country.
لطالما أردت أن أقول ذلك فى هذا البلد
Finally, my plea to you is to allow yourselves, and your children,
وأخيرا ، مناشدتي لكم هو السماح لأنفسكم ، ولأطفالكم ،
and anyone you know, to kind of fiddle with stuff,
وأي شخص تعرفوه، للعبث بهذه الأشياء ،
because it's by fiddling with things that you, you know,
لأنه العبث مع الأشياء التي ، كما تعلمون ،
you complement your other learning. It's not a replacement,
فأنت تكمل بقية تعليمك . إنه ليس بديلاً.
it's just part of learning that's important.
ولكنة فقط جزء مهم من التعليم .
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
Now -- oh, oh yeah, go on then, go on.
الآن ، أوه ، أوه نعم ،فلتمضوا قدما بعد ذلك ، فلتمضوا قدما.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)